<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of God incarnate or the vvord made flesh, cleered up: or, A vindication of certain scriptures (produced to prove the divinity of Jesus Christ) from the corrupt glosses, false interpretations, and sophistical argumentations of M. John Knowles, who denies the divinity of Christ. Also, certain annotations and observations upon a pamphlet entituled, A confession of faith concerning the holy Trinity, according to the scriptures: together with a copie of a letter sent by him to the Committee of Gloucester, concerning his faith touching the doctrine of the Trinity. By Samuel Eaton, teacher of the church of Christ at Duckenfield. Whereunto is annexed the attestation of Philip Nye, John Owen, Joseph Caryl, Tho. Harrison, William Greenhill, Sydr. Simpson, Geo. Griffiths.</title>
            <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74644</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868232</idno>
  <idno type="VID">169890</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240957568</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1379_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209349</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868232</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868232e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74644)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169890)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1379[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of God incarnate or the vvord made flesh, cleered up: or, A vindication of certain scriptures (produced to prove the divinity of Jesus Christ) from the corrupt glosses, false interpretations, and sophistical argumentations of M. John Knowles, who denies the divinity of Christ. Also, certain annotations and observations upon a pamphlet entituled, A confession of faith concerning the holy Trinity, according to the scriptures: together with a copie of a letter sent by him to the Committee of Gloucester, concerning his faith touching the doctrine of the Trinity. By Samuel Eaton, teacher of the church of Christ at Duckenfield. Whereunto is annexed the attestation of Philip Nye, John Owen, Joseph Caryl, Tho. Harrison, William Greenhill, Sydr. Simpson, Geo. Griffiths.</title>
                  <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Knowles, John, fl. 1646-1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38], 248, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Cripps, and Lodowick Lloyd, in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains only the 38-page preface.</note>
                  <note>With an additional letterpress titlepage which reads: The mystery of God incarnate, or, The word of made flesh, cleared up. Or, A vindication of certain scriptures (produced to prove the divinity of Jesus Christ) .. London, Printed for Lodowick Lloyd, and Henry Cripp[s,], and are to be sold at their shop in Popes-head-Alley.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf is an errata leaf, pasted on the stub of signature R5.</note>
                  <note>In part a reply to: Biddle, John 1615-1662  A confession of faith touching the Holy Trinity, according to the Scripture.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "October 5th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Jesus Christ --  Divinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Biddle, John, 1615-1662. --  A confession of faith touching the Holy Trinity, according to the Scripture.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:1"/>
            <p>THE MYSTERY OF <hi>GOD INCARNATE: OR, The</hi> VVORD <hi>made Flesh,</hi> cleered up: Or, A Vincication of certain Scriptures (produced to prove the Divinity of Jesus Christ) from the corrupt Glosses, false Interpretations, and sophisticall Argumentations of M. <hi>John Knowles,</hi> who denies the Divinity of <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also, Certain Annotations and Observations upon a Pamphlet entituled, <hi>A Confession of Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the holy Trinity, according to the Scriptures:</hi> Together with a copie of a Letter sent by him to the Committee of <hi>Gloucester,</hi> concerning his Faith touching the doctrine of the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Eaton,</hi> Teacher of the Church of CHRIST at <hi>Duckenfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is annexed the Attestation of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philip Nye,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>John Owen,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Joseph Caryl,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tho. Harrison,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Greenhill,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sydr. Simpson,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geo. Griffiths.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Cripps,</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Lloyd,</hi> in Popes-head Alley. 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonial">
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:2"/>
            <head>An Attestation to the ensu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatise.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all the Saints of God are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlastingly obliged to seek and contend for the glory and honour of him, whose inheritance and purchase they are, so especially is this duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on them, whom he inables from above, and calls forth to declare his Name unto the residue of the sonnes of men; this they have in charge, of this they must give an account, the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station of himselfe, and all things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is concerned, being an effectuall means to draw sinners to the faith of him, and obedience to him which he doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: this is the designe of the insuing Treatise, even a vindication of that glory of our blessed Saviour, which it is even astonishable to think, that any calling themselves by his Name should once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb facs="tcp:169890:3"/>to divest him of; it is the glory of his being, as to that nature of his, wherein he was eternally glorious, and without which he could not be a meet Mediator to bring his many sonnes to glory.</p>
            <p>There hath scarce pass'd an age since the Incarnation of the Sonne of God, wherein the old enemy of mankind hath not attempted by sundry instruments to oppugne his Deity, whereby himselfe was conquered; he knowes where the Churches great strength lies, and what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is the unshaken foundation of the purchased salvation; no wonder then if he turn himself into all forms, and improve his skill to the utmost for the removing of that corner-stone, that all our faith and hope might fall to the ground; this he sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilly indeavours by the opposer thereof, whom you shall find confuted in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise; a man who by sundry dextrous insinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, and such advantages as seducers for a season are seldome unfurnished withall, hath disturbed the peace of many, and (as we heare) overthrown the faith of not a
<pb facs="tcp:169890:3"/>few. Thou wilt find how by a faithfull labourer in the vineyard of the Lord, his sophisms are resolv'd, his corrupt glosse re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, false and subtill reasonings answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the eternall truth of the eternall Deity of the Son of God, cleared from the impotent assault of an unthankfull creature. It is our desire, and shall be our prayer, that the Lord would make this serious and so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Discourse effectuall to disintangle poor souls from the snare of the Devill, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover them from such mis-believing thoughts of the Lord Christ, as wil certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drown them in perdition, as also to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish those that are shaken, and to build up all to whom by providence it shall come, in the faith of the Son of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philip Nye,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Owen,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Joseph Caryl,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Greenhill.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sidr. Simpson,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Geo. Griffiths,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tho. Harison.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:4"/>
            <head>To the faithful and dearly beloved, the Saints of Jesus Christ, in, and about <hi>Chester;</hi> Especially to all such who have known the Doctrine, read the Papers of M. <hi>John Knowls,</hi> and who have been his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Hearers and Followers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian friends, whom I love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the Lord Christ, I have been jealous over you with godly jealousie, lest <hi>as the Serpent beguiled</hi> Eve, <hi>so your</hi> godly mindes <hi>should be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ.</hi> When M. <hi>Knowls</hi> first came among you, and was under some suspicion of unsoundness in the doctrine of the Trinity, I warned many among you to take heed of him; not because I envied him (the searcher of hearts is witness) but because I loved you and sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely sought your welfare. When I more perfectly understood his tenent against the Godhead of Christ, (which (to use M. <hi>John Goodwin</hi>'s words) hath a malignant influence upon the whole Gospel of Christ) I professed against it as heretical, as blasphemous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Christ as destructive to the faith of Jesus and damnable to all that should continue to adhere to it: and I told some of you in his presence, that my opinion
<pb facs="tcp:169890:5"/>was, that he was sent among you in wrath, and not in mercy. But all that I spake, was a Paradox unto you; you could not receive it, but I was as a mad man in your account, and all was wrath and passion in your understanding.</p>
            <p>But my designe is not to grieve any of you; therefore I'll forbear to rip up, and leave it to God to judge of these things. Afterward I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested some few Scriptures and Arguments toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and presented them unto you, at such time when the most of you were convened together; (my tender care over you (God knoweth) that you might be in nothing damnified by that horrid do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that was brought unto you, was the sole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centive that set me on work:) and I gained from you a confession of your Faith in that point, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the tenour of the Paper that I had read among you: you were then firm and unshaken in the Faith; and if it be otherwise at this day, that which is corrupt will be burnt up, and my hope is that your precious souls will be saved in the day of the Lord Jesus. There must be something that must hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all flesh that God alone may be exalted in every soul that is his.</p>
            <p>For your sakes also it was (that your faith might stand not in the words of men that are sent among you to try you, but in the power of God, which came upon you when you first believed) that I desired, and in some kinde endeavoured his removal from among you, because I saw that your
<pb facs="tcp:169890:5"/>affection to his person and parts would certainly be a snare to many of you, and inslave you to his doctrine, which was not like to want a specious presentment to commend it to you: Not that I wished one hair of his head to fall to the ground to his hurt, (the Lord he knoweth) but my earnest desire was, that you might be kept from evil.</p>
            <p>Nor had I any designe to reinvest my self into place, or power, or profit, or honour among you; for then I might have continued in the place, and in the power and profit of it, while I possessed it; for no one took it from me, nor could do, while I faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully discharged it; but I voluntarily quitted it, because I could not fulfil my Ministery to another people, and yet live among you: and you your selves know, that I travelled some miles in <hi>York</hi>-shire, to procure the blessing of an able Ministery among you; but the man whom I designed for you, was designed by God to another people in <hi>Berwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I saw that he was like to abide, at least for a time among you, I then attempted the separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of you from him, and pressed the duty (with the Apostles authority) of withdrawing from him, because he brought not the doctrine of Christ which you had received, and upon which your souls had been built; and I had the concurrence of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Churches both of the South and of the North therein, that walked in the same way and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with your selves; but this was fruitless also, though I have much peace and comfort in it; for
<pb facs="tcp:169890:6"/>I sought not my self, but your good in it.</p>
            <p>But what reason was there (may some one ask) that I should be thus active among you more then other men? Oh Brethren the flames of your ardent affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to me, and desires after me (some of you standing in neerness and dearness of relation to me, and others of you combining together to invite me and call me among you, being willing to resigne up your souls (which are the most precious parts of your selves) to my watchfulness in the Lord) enkindled my zeal and love towards you all, so that it was the more grievous to think that any soul among you should perish, by sucking in the poison of asps that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the tongue of one whom you put into the bosome of love.</p>
            <p>But all this while (while I had no rest in my spirit, but was striving with God in my prayers for you night and day, and using all means with you and for you, that you might be saved from the infection of so malignant a Doctrine) he was among you, and at work he was, in stilling (as there was occasion) his principles into you, and applying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self with all seriousness unto the answering of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per which I had (for your strengthning in the faith) presented to you: and your expectation was great of the finishing of that Work, and the approbation of many of you was greater when it was finished: And it was looked upon by some among you, and spoken of to be an unanswerable Piece, carrying the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Truth along with it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:6"/>
            <p> And indeed, I will grant it, it might well deceive some of you, who have not read of the depths of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan in <hi>Arrius</hi> and his followers, but have imagined that all that he hath held out unto you concerning this point, was never known to the world before, and that he had received it all from God inasmuch as he renounced Tradition, and gave himself to God, and to the study of the Scriptures and that then God came in to him, and revealed this secret to him, that was hid from ages: But the Heresie is ancient, and hath been often raked into and revived by many; and I do know where (for substance) all he presents may be found, and much more then he hath made use of: yet I disparage not his parts, but wish from my soul that they were improved in the knowledge and love of the Truth, and sanctified unto your salvation.</p>
            <p>When this Answer was come out and sent unto me, I saw subtilty enough in it, by which the mindes not onely of the simple but of some that were more intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, might possibly be deceived; and I presently conceived that there was now no way but one to be taken, to deliver you out of the hands of the destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, who kills you by denying Christ, while he pretends to preach the Gospel of salvation through Christ un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. I will not say that he doth this willingly, but perhaps through ignorance, and by the seductions of others, or because <hi>when he knew the Truth</hi> (for he was <hi>enlightned</hi> with the knowledge of it, as himself confesseth) <hi>he received it not in the love of it</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (it may be) <hi>God hath given him up to strong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lusious,
<pb facs="tcp:169890:7"/>to believe lyes,</hi> to his own and others hurt and hazard. I discerned, I say, that now all other at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts must cease, and that I must apply my self to a Reply to his Answer, and must commit it to Gods blessing, if so be the Lord may be pleased to convince any poor soul by it: which I have now done and do commend it in prayer to the hands of the Lord, who knows how to carry any truth in it, to your hearts.</p>
            <p>And now, Brethren, I do exhort and beseech you, especially so many of you as have received from his mouth this Doctrine (which is so contrary to what you have formerly heard, and have believed) or which have read his Papers, in which he so largely handles it, and all others who are any way affected with his person, or with his parts and gifts, or seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing graces, or with his life and conversation, and so may more readily embrace his opinion; and all such who have any questionings in their hearts, or doubtings in their mindes about Christs Godhead, especially if any among you have left their first faith, and have turned aside to this new Doctrine, or old Errour; and all such whosoever, <hi>that love the Lord Jesus Christ</hi> and the Truth <hi>in sincerity,</hi> and would be confirmed and strengthened in the Faith, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to encounter with gainsayers; I do intreat you all, for the sake of Jesus Christ, that you would in conscience to God, and to your souls, read and peruse with all seriousness, and with much prayer, this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversal Tractate, which is of the highest conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb facs="tcp:169890:7"/>and concernment (whatever you may think) that ever you had to do with. For your sakes and for the Truths sake, which I love, I have engaged in it; if it profit you not, yet my labour is with the Lord.</p>
            <p>I have very much avoided harshness, that I might offend none of you: and if there be any passages that relish not, be not offended at the Truth for such pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages sake: and if you think you discover weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses in many things that are held out to you, yet consider whether there be not strength also in many other things which are presented to your view; and let that which hath strength, have a strong impres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion upon you, and a deep entrance into you: take heed of shutting out any light, or of arguing against your consciences: take heed of prejudice in your spirits, or of respect of persons; beware lest affection should darken your judgements: flee from temptations which the shame of retracting, or of changing and altering your opinion, may expose you to. But if any of you have erred, give glory to God, who would not suffer you to abide in Errour, but had mercy on you. It is the greatest honour, to be ashamed of evil. If you should any of you stifle light within you, and struggle against that which is truth in your hearts, and should studie to uphold a person, or a party, or an opinion, because you have upheld it, God will not take pleasure in you. But I hope better things of you, and things that accompany salvation, though I thus speak.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:8"/>
            <p> My Work is not yet ended, my Reply not yet finish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his Papers not yet answered; much is yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde; it would have swelled to too great a Volume, to have done it all at once; and I was counselled against it; and I should have tired out many in their expectations while they would be waiting for it, and much more hurt might have been done in the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim while I might be long about it: Therefore I thought it my duty, as timely as I could, to give you a taste of my Labours: if the Lord be pleased to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sper my work, I may prevent the further spread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of so great an Errour, and the further leaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the hearts of men with it, by the interposition of a part of that which I purpose to present you with; and by that means also, I shall have time, while your mindes are exercised about this part, to finish the whole work.</p>
            <p>And if any shall think that I have wronged my self or the Work by putting it out of my hands by parts and pieces, I shall onely intreat them to read what is done: they will easily discern that I have encountred with him wherein his great strength lieth: and if I prosper in this, and prevail, themselves will readily confess that there will be no great doubt to be made of the rest.</p>
            <p>I have much work yet to do: some Scriptures are to be vindicated, and all the Arguments that I produced, must be freed from his evasions, and must be further confirmed and strengthened. And I purpose to hold forth the dangerousness and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperateness
<pb facs="tcp:169890:8"/>of his Errour, and to shew that the Foundation is overturned by it; and I look up to God for his further help and assistance, and take my leave of you all, beseeching the Lord to direct, guide, confirm, and settle you both in the Truth, and in the love of it, and remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to serve you in the Gospel of Truth, SA. EATON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:9"/>
            <head>Observations upon M. KNOWLS his Epistle to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Thought to have passed over the Epistle (which he fixeth to the ensuing Debate) in silence, because my scope was to avoid prolixity, and not weary the Reader with an unnecessary discourse: But because I understand that the Reader (to whom he directs it) hath not passed it by without passing his verdict upon it, I shall also present the Reader with some of my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions concerning it.</p>
            <p>I do easily understand that some mens designes are to be admired by presenting something to the Vulgar which they can apprehend: and my Antagonist appears to me (and to very many others who have read his Epistle) to be one of them.</p>
            <p>His first undertaking is, to commend Truth; but he wraps himself in the dark clouds of obscure expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and (to use his own words) he enshrines his dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course in the dark shadows of conceited phrases; so that if himself understand himself in some of his sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, (I dare say) few others do.</p>
            <p>What this <hi>every Truth</hi> is, that proceeds from the
<pb facs="tcp:169890:10"/>Divine mysterie, seeing all Truth proceeds from God, who is the Divine Mystery. And what this Divine Mystery is, whenas there are many Divine Mysteries, the Father, the Son, the Spirit, the Gospel, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, being all of them Divine Mysteries; and what God in Christ is seeing he denies the Godhead in Christ; and what Mystery is in God in Christ seeing Christ is not God, but a meer creature consisting of body and soul as other men, as he holds, is hard to be understood, and requires an interpreter.</p>
            <p>But these sayings, more especially, are not very intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible: <hi>Truth is enshrined in a dark shadow, The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry centre and soul of corporal appearances, purposely inured to sense:</hi> And, <hi>Reason is of progenie more then humane, heartned by a divine power,</hi> &amp;c. And, <hi>Reason, in the invention of Truth, obtains a greater prize, and greater praise:</hi> And, <hi>Truth draws her breath in the Divine Mystery of God in Christ, and therein is centred up in unity.</hi> These sentences are shadowed in darkness, requiring (but not deserving) some learned Commentator. What these corporal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances are, of which Truth is the centre and soul; how Truth proceeding from the Divine Mystery, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ured to Sense; how Reason is of progenie more then humane since the Fall, seeing both Men and Reason have lost God, and cannot tell where to finde him; and see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both are degenerate, and cannot call God Father so much as the rest of the creatures can: and how Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son hath the invention of Truth for its greater prize or praise, seeing <hi>the natural man,</hi> with all his Reason <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb facs="tcp:169890:10"/>understand the things of God:</hi> and how every Truth that proceeds from the Divine Mystery, draweth her breath forth from God in Christ, and is centred up in unity: How such Riddles must be expounded, and how such mystical Positious must be interpreted, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be consonant either to Reason, or to Scripture, let him that can (M. <hi>Knowls</hi> excepted) shew.</p>
            <p>There is also some frothy vanity which he takes pleasure in, because his discourse is full of it; he fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies words which sound alike, or begin with one letter, or are terminated with like syllables; which is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together so suitable to his professed Christian gravity. I shall give some few instances; <hi>heartned, heightned; unskilfull, willfull; wicked, weaponed; traduc't, traitors; fail, fall; preservation, expugnation,</hi> and many more; which affectation of words will perish as the grass; but he harpes upon it in his sentences.</p>
            <p>After commendation of Truth, he comes to exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and excites all professors to try all things yea to examine principles; and under that head, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of Christian Religion it selfe may come, and also the Scriptures must be tried whether they be the Word of God, and whether there be any such thing as a Christ or not, and whether Mahomet or Christ be the greater Prophet, seeing there is a great contention betwixt Turkes and Christians about that point.</p>
            <p>He shews also the designe of the Treatise that he was upon, and calls it <hi>a Logical Question, Whether Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ, the Son of the most high God, be that God:</hi> Which I have alwaies thought to be <hi>a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical
<pb facs="tcp:169890:11"/>and Divine Question,</hi> and to be received by Faith, and not searched out by Reason. And with this distinction of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>that God,</hi> or, <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>the most high God,</hi> granting Christ to be God, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying him to be the most high God, he hath cloaked and covered the horridness of his Opinion; and it hath been the bait whereby he hath allured many to swallow it down. Poor souls have pleaded his cause with such expressions: <hi>He denies not Christ to be God, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts not from Christ, he exalts him, and sets him up in glory;</hi> and they <hi>never heard Christ held forth in greater clearness and lustre then he hath set him forth:</hi> whereas they consider not that he hath infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly debased him in making him a Creature-God; and if he should strip him of all his created glory at the next Bout, and make him baser then a worm, and tread him under feet as the dust of the earth, he could not so much dishonour him and vilifie him, as he hath done, in taking his Divinity from him. The distance betwixt an Angel and a Worm, is but finite; but the distance betwixt God and a Creature (as glorious as you can think of) is infinite.</p>
            <p>He saith, <hi>The nature of this Question calls for the greatest, the gravest consideration;</hi> and if so, then the salvation of men is concerned in it; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I have much contended for, but have been thought to be harsh and rigid in maintaining of it: but he hath preached, that it was sufficient for persons to believe that Jesus Christ is Lord, and that God raised him from the dead, though they were ignorant whether he were the
<pb facs="tcp:169890:11"/>most high God, or a meer Creature: How is it then, in his account, of greatest and gravest consideration?</p>
            <p>He presents the weightiness of the knowledge of this Question in three Arguments which he produceth, fetched from the Excellencie, Mysterie, and Utilitie of this Knowledge. But of the Excellency I may say as the Apostle (in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10.) saith of all the glory of the Law, when he compares it with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, that it was not glorious in comparison of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that excelleth: so it may be said of the knowledge of Christ, If he be but a meer man, consisting of soul and body, as he makes him, there is no excellency in the knowledge of him, in comparison of that excellency which he takes from him, which will be in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him to be God and Man united together in one person: For the excellency of the knowledge, is derived from the excellency of the thing known: by how much then the most high God is more excellent then any Creature, by so much the knowledge of Christ, as the most high God, is more excellent then the knowledge of him as a meer Creature, how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent soever any one may imagine him. And as the love of the Father, in giving Christ, and of Christ in giving himself, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16. and <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.13. (if Christ be the Son of his own Nature and Essence, by eternal gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration) is superlatively great and glorious, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of what it is if he be but a created, made Son, like the Angels: so the knowledge of this love of God and Christ is transcendently high and excellent, if we know it in reference to the excellency of such a Person, so given; the knowledge of the love of such a Christ pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth knowledge, and the knowledge of the love of the
<pb facs="tcp:169890:12"/>Father in giving such a Christ, passeth knowledge; we may proclaime the heighth and depth, the length and breadth of it; for it is not to be parallel'd.</p>
            <p>But he also makes the knowledge of Christ in the excellency of it, to arise from the person, whom he saith lay in the womb of eternit, and it was excellent in that respect.</p>
            <p>But did not all other things lie in the womb of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity in his sence, as well as Christ? for he speaks onely of Gods eternall purpose to create Christ in time. And Gods counsels creating all things, were in this womb of eternity; and what preeminence then had Christ, in this respect, above other creatures, that the excellencie of his knowledge should hence be argued? But with high expressions, wherein (when examined) there is nothing but emptiness, he captivates the mindes of the inconsiderate. But to say that the knowledge of Christ hath excellencie in it, because it is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him that not onely lay in, but proceeded from the womb of Eternity, in that eternal generation which he had from the Father; this hath not the form of truth, but the truth it self of all excellencie in it.</p>
            <p>And, according to our Tenent, the Righteousness of God is lifted up in greater glory: for he that was able to bear Gods wrath to the utmost, and to subsist under it, without being overwhelmed and consumed by it, such an one was able to give a sufficient price to God for sin, to pay the utmost farthing of the debt of the Elect, and to satisfie Justice in the utmost de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; which no meer humane creature (such as he makes Christ onely to be) could do; but such a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son who is God-Man, which we assert Christ to be:
<pb facs="tcp:169890:12"/>and the knowledge of this hath incomparable excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie in it.</p>
            <p>And the Righteousness of Christ also is made the righteousness of God according to our assertion, and as the Scripture affirmeth; which is more excellent then the righteousness of a meer man, and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it more full of lustre and glory. And the Truth of God, Holiness of God, Hatred of Sin, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrencie of Unrighteousness, do all shine forth with ravishing astonishment to the eyes of every spiritual be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder, when God would not spare his natural Son, the Son of his own Self, but (having imputed the sins of the Elect unto him) delivered him up, and prosecuted him with all his wrath, (as if he had been the greatest malefactor and transgressor) and fetched out thereby an infinite satisfaction to himself from him, that was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and able to give it. And the unsearchable Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge of God (which the Angels and the Church have always admired and adored) who hath found out a way of satisfying Himself by Himself, and yet in our nature, (which was necessary, because the offence was in our nature) shines forth in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of beauty in Christ, the Son of God, who subsisteth in the nature of God, and assumed Flesh. And indeed, all the Attributes of glory do meet in their perfect excellencie, in the Mysterie of Christ, or God Incarnate: and there we may see them; and the sight of them hath such transcendencie of splendor, that it dazzles the sight of all persons that do contemplate them: But let Christ be stripped of his Godhead, and the glory of the knowledge of Christ departs away with it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:13"/>
            <p> In a word, In the knowledge of Christ, we have the knowledge of the Father in his full proportion; we see him as he is in Christ: As face answers to face in a glass, so doth Christ, the essential Son of God, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer the Father in all things; insomuch as Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self told <hi>Philip,</hi> that <hi>he that hath seen him, hath seen the Father:</hi> which cannot be spoken of any fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite creature, because of the infinite distance betwixt God and it. So that there is in the knowledge of this mysterie Christ, a great depth of glory, as we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and believed it; but, according to him, it may be soon fathomed.</p>
            <p>But he urgeth the Reader to acquire the knowledge of Christ the Son from the Mysterie that is in it. There is Mysterie in it indeed, to him that contemplates it, as the truth is in Christ. What greater Mysterie, then two Natures in one Person? the Nature of man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Person of man? the Son as ancient as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? begotten of the Father, yet not in any time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten? another Person from the Father, and yet not another God? Nature and Essence communicated to him, and yet he not dependent, nor less perfect? This is such a Mysterie as Scripture doth assert, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to be received by faith; because there is a depth in it, which Reason cannot pry into. And he disputes against it as impossible, and cries out against it of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictious that he saith are in it: he would number it with his Reason, being resolved not to receive any thing which he cannot understand: but Reason cannot reach it; the wisdom of man is foolishness in searching into and discussing this secret; Reason is confounded; and the attempts of Rational men, in seeking to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend
<pb facs="tcp:169890:13"/>it, are madness; they might as rationally attempt to reach heaven with their hand: therefore Christians must be pressed to get Faith, that they may measure the length and bredth of it.</p>
            <p>But according to his Position of the Son, that he is a meer Creature, consisting of soul and body, Where is the Mysterie? where is the Secret? where is the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfulness of Christ? If in his person he be in all things like unto other men, and be constituted of the same constitutive parts, Where is the separateness, the remoteness and transcendencie of his person compared with others? For that is the mysterie, <hi>viz.</hi> the myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Person, which he sends us to studie out. As for the wonder of works wrought by the vertue and power of God that is another thing; but our Dispute respects the Person. Nor is there any such secret in it, that a meer man should do mighty things by the power of God, inasmuch as the Prophets and Apostles have done things (in the ages in which they lived) by Gods power; and of the Apostles (as instruments in Gods hand) it is said, that they did <hi>greater</hi> things, material<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly considered, then Christ himself: yea, we read that God made <hi>the sounding of rams horns</hi> (in which there was little vertue to such a purpose) instrumental for the casting down of the walls of <hi>Jericho;</hi> and we can easily dive into the depth, and come unto the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of this by our Reason: This therefore cannot be the Mysterie of Christ; but the Mysterie is God Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, or, the Flesh and Nature of Man assumed and taken up unto an hypostatical union with the Son (who is very God) which this Tractate undertakes to prove.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:14"/>
            <p> His third Argument (wherewith he excites the Reader to gain the knowledge of the Son) is the Utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of this knowledge.</p>
            <p>We grant the Utilitie of it, and enforce it upon undeniable grounds as we determine the Question: but he destroys the benefit which comes by Christ, in hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the negative of the Question, <hi>viz.</hi> that Christ is not <hi>that God</hi> is not <hi>the most high God;</hi> which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I shall endeavour to make out largely with such clearness (through Gods help) as may convince gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayers.</p>
            <p>Christ, God-Man is the very life of Believers; he is their Peace, he is their Hope, he is their Rock upon which their souls are built, and the gates of hell shall not prevail against them; he is their Shadow from the wrath of God; he is their Strength, unto all that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers are called to do or suffer in this evil world; he is their Comforter, in his Advocateship, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of his Spirit in their souls; he is their All in All: Faith may act upon a Christ with greatest assurance, in all conditions, in all necessities and temptations; and with great sweetness hath the fainting weary soul been supported and born up, in the meditations of such a strong, mighty, great, and glorious Christ, who is God, very God, the most high God, with us in our nature. But he takes away the Utilitie of all that either Christ is, or hath, or did, or suffered; the Utility of his Person, in that union that Saints have with it; the Uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of his Offices, in that communion which Saints have with them; the Utilitie of his Righteousness, it can be but his own righteousness, and cannot be made over to others; if he be but a meer man, it is due, and cannot
<pb facs="tcp:169890:14"/>be imputed for others righteousness; the Utilitie of his Death, of his Resurrection, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Merit of them, is the Utility of them; and it is destroyed by him with the Godhead, as I shall shew when I shall come to handle it.</p>
            <p>As for the many Prophecies that are chained up in darkness, if Christ be not in the mystery of him known: It is true, that the Prophets speak much of Christ in their writings, and the whole Scripture also, concerning the Godhead of Christ; and we are in darkness, and are even confounded what sence to put upon them, if Christ be not <hi>that God,</hi> or <hi>the most high God.</hi> But what those Scriptures are that are brought out of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity (which were imprisoned in darkness before) by the stating of the Question (as he resolves it of Christ, making him a man onely, and nothing more) he might have done well to have declared, because the Reader will be in the dark about it. If he mean the Scriptures produced by him in this Controversie, I hope I have made it to appear, so far as I have proceeded in my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer of them, that he put them into darkness by unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and ingenuine sences that he hath put upon them. But let the Reader decide that betwixt us.</p>
            <p>Whereas he maketh it eternal life, and no less, to know Christ in his person as he hath determined the Question, Doth he not conclude, by consequence, that, to be ignorant of it, as he holds it, is to fall short of eternal life, and to lose it? And doth he not conclude all others that differ from him in this doctrine that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects the person of Christ, to be in the state of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation? and if they shall adhere still to their own opinion, opposite to what he hath held out, that such
<pb facs="tcp:169890:15"/>must needs perish? And is it not as high as ever I as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted in that last Debate which I had in <hi>Chester,</hi> in the presence of so many, concerning the knowledge of the Deity of Christ, which I made necessary to salvation; for which I fell under such deep censure of harshness, and became, as some told me, a great offence to the weaker Christians? and in reference to his assertion, this is currant doctrine: he may sentence men to death everlasting, according to his fancie, and yet it is a fault in me to shew the danger of so high an Heresie accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scripture.</p>
            <p>It is also to be observed that this very text of <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.14 when I brought it to prove the damnableness of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying Christs Godhead, it would not be granted that it respected the person of Christ, but the sending of him; but now it is applied by him to the Person, and passeth well enough. His last words under this Head of Utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>(viz. 'tis to know the being of all knowledge, and the centre of every being)</hi> are expressions very sutable to such a Christ as we contend for; but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inconsistent to a Creature-Christ, which cannot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umbrate the Father in such perfection (as the Scripture he alleadgeth shews) that he that knoweth the one, knoweth the other also.</p>
            <p>After he had baited the hook with the colourable Arguments of the Excellency Mystery, and Utility of the knowledge of such a Subject, to bring them to an examination and revisal of their principles, he casts out the line in some awakening and quickening Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to draw them to the net of his own delusions; and there is a great deal of <hi>cunning craftiness</hi> in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working. Their rootedness and setledness in the
<pb facs="tcp:169890:15"/>Faith a long time together he cals it but a state of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and darkness which they have been in and he would shake them out of it, and invites them and excites them to a consideration of the things that he would present to their view. And because all judging requires a Rule according to which it must be made, and God designes the Scripture to be the Rule by which Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Truth and Errour may be discerned I looked when he would have sent the Reader thither, to the serious perusal and study of it, because the nobleness of the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> was in the searching of it: but there is a deep si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in this respect, and another Rule is exalted; <hi>the spirit of Oneness,</hi> and <hi>divine revelation</hi> that works in them is mentioned, and nothing else; by which spirit himself at first received this Doctrine, as was collected from some expressions of his. And he speaks of a <hi>spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual light,</hi> and <hi>intelligent perswasion</hi> and of <hi>seeing with ones own eyes,</hi> and of <hi>truth written upon a mans own soul;</hi> and in all these expressions he draws off from the standing Rule, which is appointed to measure all things by; yea, the very things that he hath mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The spirit that is in men, may be a spirit of Satan, and not of God, unless tried by the Scripture, that was indited by the Spirit of God; for such a spirit is now gone forth into the world. The divine revelation may be a diabolical delusion, unless it come with Scripture-impression upon it. The spiritual light may be darkness unless it can abide the Scripture-light and unite with it. There is also Errour written upon the heart, as well as Truth; and a man cannot be at a certainty what is written, unless it be compared with Scripture-writing to finde out the agreement or disagreement. And for see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:169890:16"/>with a mans own eyes; a man is like to see but a little Truth with them, unless Scripture enlighten them.</p>
            <p>But is not the Spirit necessary to interpret Scripture?</p>
            <p>The Spirit interprets Scripture by Scripture; that is, in a mans studie of the Scriptures, the Spirit is sent to lead persons unto remembrance of other Scriptures, and suggests what is written elsewhere, and helps the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing to extract a right sence from hence: and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit makes use of others gifts and light, but still accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures: but he passeth over this without the least touch.</p>
            <p>In the next place, he warns of two extremes he speaks of, <hi>lifting up the heel against the truth;</hi> and calls this <hi>wantonness,</hi> but mistakes the term or expression very much; he might have called it perverseness, peevishness, pertinaciousness, but not wantonness; for wantonness is a foolish facility to please their own fancie, in receiving something which they should not so lightly have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; to which too many are inclined else there would not be such sudden changes in such high and weighty things of greatest concernment: and this is the facility which he mentions as the second extreme.</p>
            <p>He comes over again with this double extreme, but in other words. He speaks of some that <hi>draw the curtains to shut out light,</hi> and calls them <hi>luxuriant and heady spirits;</hi> but stumbles again in the terms: for a luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant and heady man is one that runs headlong from one opinion to another, and is not staid, and sober, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest, and cautious in his entertaining Doctrine, but is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant in the reception of all that at first likes him: but he makes it to be a quite contrary thing; surely he would have said, or at least should have said <hi>tenacious</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:169890:16"/>in stead of <hi>luxuriant:</hi> there are persons which will hold what they have held, and shut out all further light then they have received, which is doubtless a fault; and others are luxuriant, and heady, and hastie, and rash, and too easily welcom all that is presented for truth: and indeed, he might speak this experimentally of this extreme, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause too many welcomed his doctrine, as if it had come from heaven to them; but they will know in time that they were mistaken.</p>
            <p>Now his designe is in all this to fetch off from ancient truth received, and then to fasten them upon this new Doctrine, that when they have received it, they might not depart from it againe. And this appeares from these words; <hi>They are as soon drawn off, as dallyed to it.</hi> But my hope is, that such precious soules whom he hath unsettled, God will never suffer to settle upon his bottome.</p>
            <p>After this, he expresseth himselfe insinuatingly, and with plausible attractives, to incline the minds and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men to attend seriously to him. His Doctrine that he brings to them is the mystery of the Father and of Christ, and it hath been hid, and God hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested it to him; and haply it may be the time that God will have so much mercy as to manifest it to them by him; for this is the sence of his expressions. And the received Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> he makes to be Antichristian, and call's it <hi>the smoake of the Pit;</hi> and his Opinion he call's, <hi>the glory of the Lord:</hi> And because some were taken with it, therefore he thinkes the glory of the Lord is ascending for the breaking of the cloud, and for the ushering in of the day; thus he flatters himself, and allures them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:17"/>
            <p> But he knows very well that this <hi>mysterie of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which he calls <hi>the mysterie of the Father,</hi> and of <hi>Christ,</hi> hath not been hid unto this day, and is now newly manifested but hath been of old made known to the world, and in every age there have been some that have disturbed the Saints with it; &amp; he knows that God suffered it once to overspread the world; but after the darkening, the glory of the Lord in the truth of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Christ, and mysterie of the Trinity did arise again, and the wrath of God overtook him in a remarkable judgement that first broached it among men; and God brought both him and it to nought.</p>
            <p>But he makes an Objection concerning the producing and publishing such Questions for the troubling of the people, and answers it, but not with godly simplicity and sincerity, as becomes the Gospel.</p>
            <p>He saith his designe was <hi>that the doctrine formerly received might have better foundations, and that the seemingly-fair face of many mental buildings may be searched, and their body examined to the very basis;</hi> and so he pretends to <hi>do nothing against the truth, but for the truth;</hi> and that his scope is not to destroy the doctrine formerly received, but to make bare the foundation of it to make it firmer, that it may carry the building, that the former doctrine may come to be further ratified, and more firmly established. But if this be so what means the importunate exhortations to the Reader, in the precedent parts of his Epistle? In one place he saith, <hi>See with your own eyes that the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel of traducal doctrines, authorized onely by man, may fail and fall.</hi> And in another place, <hi>That which I have to mediate with thee for, in reference to the
<pb facs="tcp:169890:17"/>work in hand, is, that thou wouldst not suffer tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent doctrines to become traitors to presented truths.</hi> And again in another place, <hi>Haply this may be the time that the truth of these mysteries of the Father and the Son shall be manifested. The smoke of the pit ascendeth very high; methinks it proclaims the glory of the Lord to be rising for the breaking of the cloud, and the ushering in of the day.</hi> Are these expressions to build up doctrine formerly received with greater sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, or to destroy them? Therefore there is fraud or falshood in his expressions. If by <hi>former doctrines</hi> he mean the doctrine of the Trinity, and especially that which respects the Godhead of Christ, as it hath been formerly received by the Saints generally all along in the ages of the world; then here is Falshood: for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe is to deface, extirpate, and destroy that doctrine as his own expressions declare. But if by <hi>former doctrine</hi> he mean his own Heresie and Errour, which is not new, but of old hath troubled the Church, especially in the fourth age after Christ; then there is Fraud and deceit in his words: for his words are an Answer to an Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and they are his defence which he makes for himself; he would not be thought to trouble people with new doctrine, but to settle them in the old.</p>
            <p>In the next place he Apologizeth for the plainness of his language; but I have never heard him condemned for that by any, but for the conceitedness of his lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage he hath been censured by many.</p>
            <p>The Treatise for the matter, and the Epistle for the language, have engendred hard thoughts in the mindes of many of the most sober and truely pious Readers against him</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:18"/>
            <p> What he speakes of the rising of this Tractate in hast, intending onely a visitaton to a private Friend, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a more then earnest invitation, had need of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation. There was a small paper of Scriptures and Arguments prepared for others, to settle them in Christ's Godhead, but presented to him through the counsel of Friends, for his conviction; and he (through I know not what importunity, for it was a griefe to me when I heard of it) hastily undertakes an answer to it, which he gave out he intended to send me, (and it was sent me at second hand, but he sent it not) but sent it to the Press, and hasted it to the view of the world, which he hath cause to repent of. And his publishing of it, (notwithstanding his Plea which he makes for it) is no way justifiable, but carries injury in it against me; for he hath printed my paper, which he knew was, first, suddenly and in a few hours time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by me, and therefore was not like to be of such strength, as if it had come forth of my hands with greater deliberation. Secondly, prepared for others, and not for him. Thirdly, that it came into his hands at the request of friends for the satisfying of his scruples, if there were any in him, and for the settling of him in the received Faith. Fourthly, he tooke a large time for the answer, and deliberately sent it forth of his hands, and then published it with such disadvantage to me, and advantage to himselfe; and this he did without once acquainting me with it, or seeking my consent, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose (it may be through the counsel of friends) to gain honour to himself, and to lay me under shame: but God hath his ordering providence in it, and will turne it to his praise, and with these thoughts I sit down satisfied.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:18"/>
            <p> In the last place, he directs his speech to me, and saith, if I shall daigne to descend the sands with this Treatise of his, I must know that Reviling is no Reason, and that He adds nothing to Truth, that belcheth forth Bitterness from a distempered spirit.</p>
            <p>In these expressions of his, he would have the world to conceive, that I am such a one who exercise Reviling more then Reason, and that doth belch out bitterness from a distempered spirit; and he gives hints of it in his ensuing discourse severall times.</p>
            <p>My answer is, There was a time when he and I discus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the point of the Godhead of Christ, at which time after I had a good while exercised patience, I was at last so much stirred with his absurd, senceless, and unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable answers which he gave (for so they seemed to me) &amp; with the adherence of some that were present at that time, to him, that I called his Opinion Heresie, and said it was damnable Doctrine, and warned all present to take heed of him, and said I feared he was sent in judgment: and because he would not owne his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (though he laboured with all his might to destroy the received approved Doctrine) I told him he rather carried it like a Jesuite, then like a Christian: and all this was spoken with earnestness and vehemency of voyce, as is frequent when I discourse upon a weighty subject; when yet there was no wrath or passion; yet I do confess there was a holy indignation in me against his errour, and zeale for the truth. And he alludes to this time in his expressions; and this hath been greatly layd to my charge and objected in the greatest deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from me: but I spare the mentioning of those who have been herein most guilty.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169890:19"/>
            <p> And for my further clearing, I did in a private way to a friend present these assertions, and shall now pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish them to the world as such which I conceive will justifie me, which were grounds of such a carriage, as is censured by many of his friends.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>I believe that these are the</hi> last times <hi>spoken of,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.1. 2 Tim. 3.1, 6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>I believe that in these last times</hi> false teachers shall arise, who shall privily bring in damnable heresies, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>I do believe that these false teachers shall</hi> transform themselves into angels of light, <hi>and</hi> ministers of righteousness, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11 13, 14, 15. <hi>by which means they shall come to</hi> deceive, if it were possible, the very elect, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.24.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>I do believe that all that are sound and orthodox, and lovers of the truth, especially if they be the Ministers of Christ, they ought to</hi> contend for the faith once delivered to the Saints, <hi>Jude <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc></desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>and that they ought to watch, and to warn the people of such false Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers with all diligence both night and day,</hi> Acts 20.28, 29, 30, 31.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>I do believe that zeal ought to be put forth for the defence of the truth, and indignation shewed against heresies that do arise, and against the persons themselves, in reference to such heresies,</hi> Tit. 1.10, 11. 2 Joh. 10.11. Tit. 3.10, 11. Rom. 16.17.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>I do believe that names that carry reproach with them, and serve to vilifie such persons, may &amp; ought to be put upon them, that the godly may be warned of them, and take more heed of them,</hi> 2 Joh. 7. 2 Cor. 11.13 <hi>and that their opinions may be branded with names, to cause Saints the more to abhor them,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1, 2. <hi>Provided always, that the names that are either put upon persons, or the things they hold, do not exceed the nature of such things or crimes of the persons that hold them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>I do believe that it is no persecution either to wish evil to such persons in reference unto such opinions, or to do evil against them, that they may not have opportunity of annoying and hurring the Church of God,</hi> Gal. 5.8, 9. <hi>My reason is, because there are two things for the most part in Persecution in Scripture-acceptation, of which the latter cannot be wanting.</hi> 1. <hi>The subjects of it must be Saints,</hi> Acts 9.1.2. <hi>The Cause of it must be Righteousness,</hi> Matth. 5.10. 1 Pet. 4.14, 15. <hi>If these he wanting, it cannot be called Persecution: Provided alwaies, that the evill that is wished or attempted, do not exceed the nature of the Errour that is held and published.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>